

Filimon Abel Mgandu

Assistant Lecturer



24 June 1992



P.O Box 2077 Dodoma-Tanzania



+255 759784638



filimonabel2499@gmail.com

About me -

I am university graduate pursued Bsc with Education (Informatics and Mathematics) and Msc in Mathematical Modelling, acquired competences in mathematics, informatics, psychology, education and computer. I am an articulate individual who works in a thorough and committed manner, quickly adapts to new systems and work successfully as part of a team.

Skil

Team work

Communication skills

Research skills

Self motivation

(*)[The skill scale is from 0 (Fundamental Awareness) to 6 (Expert).]

Education

2021-Todate PhD Mathematics and Computational Science and Engineering On Progress The Nelson Mandela African Institution of Scince and Technology		
2017-2019	M.Sc. In Mathematical Modelling University of Dar es salaam.	GPA 4.3/5.0
2013-2016	B.Sc. With Education (Informatics and Mathematics) Sokoine University of Agriculture	GPA 4.4/5.0
2011-2013	Advanced Certificate of Secondary Education (ACSE) Njombe Secondary School	Dvision Two
2007-2010	Certificate of Secondary Education (CSE) Kidamali Secondary School	Dvision One
200-2006	Certificate of Primary Education Kipera Primary School	

Career Objectives

- To use informatics and mathematics in solving a wide range of problems in Economy, Education, Environments, Health, Population, Science and Technology.
- To design, build and analyse models on large data sets using statistical softwares such as R, PYTHON, MATLAB, SPSS, STATA and others.
- To mine and analyse large datasets, draw valid inferences and present them successfully to management using a reporting tools.

Research Areas

- Data science / Big data.
- · Statistics and Probability Theories.
- · Computer programming.

Research and Publications

Publications

- Filimon Abel Mgandu, Mashaka Mkandawile, Mohamed Rashid,"
 Modelling the Impacts of Climate Change on Water Level Fluctuations in Water Resources in Tanzania: A Case Study of Mtera Dam", International Journal of Mathematical Sciences and Computing (IJMSC), Vol.6, No.3, pp.22-32, 2020. DOI: 10.5815/ijmsc.2020.03.03
- Filimon Abel Mgandu, Mashaka Mkandawile, Mohamed Rashid. "
 Trend Analysis and Forecasting of Water Level in Mtera Dam Using
 Exponential Smoothing ", International Journal of Mathematical Sciences and Computing (IJMSC), Vol.6, No.4, pp.26-34, 2020. DOI:
 10.5815/ijMSC.2020.04.03

Master's thesis

 Modelling the Impacts of Climate Change on Water Level Fluctuations on Water Resources in Tanzania: A Case Study of Mtera Dam.



Filimon Abel Mgandu

Assistant Lecturer



24 June 1992



P.O Box 2077 Dodoma-Tanzania



+255 759784638



filimonabel2499@gmail.com

About me -

I am university graduate pursued Bsc with Education (Informatics and Mathematics) and Msc in Mathematical Modelling, acquired competences in mathematics, informatics, psychology, education and computer. I am an articulate individual who works in a thorough and committed manner, quickly adapts to new systems and work successfully as part of a team.

Skil

Team work

Communication skills

Research skills

Self motivation

(*)[The skill scale is from 0 (Fundamental Awareness) to 6 (Expert).]

Experience

2019-Todate Assistant Lecturer

College of Business Education

- Carrying out lectures, seminars, and tutorials for undergraduate courses
- Setting, invigilating and marking undergraduate examinations.
- Supervising projects and practical training for students.
- · Conducting research and publishing results.
- Carrying out consultancy and public service.

2016-2017 Teaching Assistant

East Coast Secondary

- · Taught mathematics and computer studies.
- Marked the quizzes, assignments, and examinations.
- Conducted extra classes to provide group and personal tutorials.
- · Supervised mathematics and ICT students clubs.

2013-2013 Teaching Assistant

Agnes Trust Secondary

- Taught mathematics and computer studies.
- Marked the quizzes, assignments, and examinations.
- Conducted extra classes to provide group and personal tutorials.
- Supervised mathematics and ICT students clubs.

Volunteering Experience

2013 National building service army at Msange Camp. Volunteering on doing community activities.

2010 Volunteered in teaching Mathematics at Kipera primary School.

Awards

2021	Research Award from Ministry of Agriculture under TANIPAC project for	
	combating aflatoxin contamination in maize.	

2019 Awarded 5000 USD from Mwalimu Julius Nyerere Memorial Scholarship Awards from Bank of Tanzania(BOT) for Research on Modelling the Impacts of Climate Change on Water Level Fluctuations on Water Resources.

2017 Mwalimu Julius Nyerere Memorial Scholarship Awards from Bank of Tanzania(BOT). Studying Masters of Science in Mathematical Modelling at University of Dar es salaam.

Vice- chancellor, Sokoine university of Agriculture. Overall Best Final Year student in B. Sc. Education.

Dean, Faculty of science, Sokoine university of Agriculture. Best Final Year student, B. Sc with Education (Informatics and mathematics).

2013 Best student in Mathematics and Economics at Njombe secondary school.



Filimon Abel Mgandu

Assistant Lecturer



24 June 1992



P.O Box 2077 Dodoma-Tanzania



+255 759784638



filimonabel2499@gmail.com

About me -

I am university graduate pursued Bsc with Education (Informatics and Mathematics) and Msc in Mathematical Modelling, acquired competences in mathematics, informatics, psychology, education and computer. I am an articulate individual who works in a thorough and committed manner, quickly adapts to new systems and work successfully as part of a team.

Skil

Team work

Communication skills

Research skills

Self motivation

(*)[The skill scale is from 0 (Fundamental Awareness) to 6 (Expert).]

Workshops, Presentations and Conferences

2022	Facilitated Training on Quantitative Research with SPSS and R
2020	Facilitated Training on Quantitative Research with SPSS
2020	Business and Economic Growth for Sustainable Development
2019	International Modelling week (At University of Rwanda)
2018	Partial differential Equations and Calculus of Variations
2018	Training on Statistical analysis using SPSS, STATA and R
2017	Training on Geographical Information systems (GIS) using ArcGIS and QGIS
2016	Capacity Building Training on UNESCO Operational Strategy
2015	Agricultural Development and production in Tanzania

Scientific Computing

Operating Systems: Windows, Linux(Ubuntu)

Software and Tools: SPSS, STATA, ArcGIS, QGIS, Mathematica, Latex, Mysql

GLPK and Microsoft office.

Programming languages:Python, R, MATLAB, Octave, C++, C and PHP.

Hobbies and interests

- · Exposure and Networking.
- · Watching football.
- · Doing physical body exercise.

Referees

• DR. NKUBA NYERERE

Sokoine University of Agriculture, Department of biometry and statistic P.O.BOX 3008, chuo-kikuu SUA, Morogoro. Mobiles: +255 767 994 591 Email: nyereren@nm-aist.ac.tz

DR. GRACE MPUYA

College of Business Education, Department of ICT and Mathematics, P.O.BOX 2077, Dodoma. Mobile1: +255 756 140 195

Email: g.mpuya@cbe.ac.tz

DR. BENEDICT KAZUZURU

Sokoine University of Agriculture, Department of biometry and statistic P.O.BOX 3008, chuo- kikuu SUA, Morogoro. Mobiles: +255 657 209 202

Email: bwenke.1999@yahoo.com